Let's move on to
the chapter on statecharts.
Especially
UML statecharts.
We had already seen flat state diagrams
at the very beginning of the lecture.
And these UML state diagrams
(state machine diagrams/statecharts) are in
principle closely related to the flat
state diagrams we have already seen.
But in particular they
offer further structuring possibilities, which
we will get to
know in a moment.
Concerning
usage.
Statecharts are
used when the
focus of modeling is on
states and transitions between them.
So a bit away
from what activity diagrams do.
In a way also the Petri
nets namely to aim at action sequences.
So putting the
actions in the foreground.
This is more about states and
state transitions of a given system.
In a way,
UML state diagrams are
rather used when there
is no typical sequence.
Rather, the focus is on
sequences and events that occur randomly
or are equally likely
to occur in any order.
This is not to say
that there are not systems that
can usefully be
modeled with Petri
nets/activity diagrams as well as
flat or UML state diagrams.
These are all
possibilities for dynamic modeling.
And there are certainly examples
where one would have a choice.
But there are also cases where one
of the two rough directions is more appropriate.
To distinguish between the two, I would
like to make this observation that activity diagrams
focus on actions and state diagrams
focus on reactions to the environment.
So a state transition is
triggered by something from outside.
And then it has to be
described what that does to the states,
or what new state is
then taken by the system.
Instead of simply putting sequences
of actions in the center.
That's very
abstract at first.
Concretely, of course, one
can find various applications.
I have only
mentioned a few.
State diagrams, whether flat
or UML state diagrams with
additional elements and representation options,
are used in various application domains.
When
describing protocols.
Components of
distributed systems.
The description of
processes in user interfaces.
Embedded
systems.
One can certainly
continue the list long.
Because states and transitions have
become a very general framework
to describe behavior in computer
science, but also in other domains.
Specifically,
the
state diagrams/statecharts as they later entered
UML date back to the late 80s.
By a scientist
named David Harel.
The original
name was statecharts.
That's why you still find that as
the name when you look for examples.
At the beginning of the
slides, in the first or second
week, I had given
an article by Mr. Harel.
That is the original
paper where statecharts were introduced.
And with about different
syntax, they later entered UML.
A major goal
of UML statecharts/statecharts is
what can happen
in flat statecharts.
Namely, to get a handle on the
fact that the state space grows a lot.
There are simply certain features
that statecharts are equipped with.
In addition to simply
states and state transitions,
which already existed in flat statecharts,
there are, for example, refinements of states.
States are not just nodes
in a graph, without internal structure.
But they can
be refined hierarchically.
And that also leads to being
able to handle a state explosion.
In addition, there is
an explicit concept of parallelism.
We have already learned
about this in various places.
In Petri
nets/activity diagrams.
That it's important to be able to express
that; or interesting to be able to model that.
In statecharts (UML and statecharts)
there is an explicit concept
here for what is
called parallel switching through regions.
Which a flat statechart does
not allow to express explicitly.
And also this will lead
us to model more compactly
in UML statecharts
than with flat statecharts.
A related feature, which
ultimately makes it easier
or possible to deal with
these two aspects, is history nodes.
I haven't had much to
say about that yet either.
We'll see when we get
that far in the example.
The main point is to
be able to remember implicitly which
states
were active last, especially
when leaving such hierarchical/nested/parallel states.
In order to be able
to resume work later when returning
to such a hierarchical/parallel connected
area of the state diagram.
Instead of having to store
this explicitly in the states.
Then there are so-called
remote triggers, or flags.
These are simply means to
enable communication in the state diagram.
Even between states that are
not explicitly connected by a transition.
Many of these features are
mainly used to make diagrams that
we use
clear and compact.
So to avoid having to
have a lot of states.
Or if you have many states,
to group them in a meaningful way.
That the diagram
still remains clear.
So the goal is a size
reduction, versus using a flat state diagram.
What will not occur here that
we switch between finite and infinite.
We usually assume flat
statecharts to be finite.
And even a finite
UML state diagram will
not correspond to an
infinite flat state diagram.
This is different
from Petri nets.
An infinite Petri net can
have an infinite reachability graph.
We will not have this
transition from finite to infinite.
But a similar size reduction or
similar behavior, with respect to size.
Where even a very small
Petri net can still have a
very large
reachability graph.
So it will
be similar here.
There can be very
compact small UML state diagrams,
but they would correspond to
very large flat state diagrams.
We'll do most of the
discussion on a concrete example.
That's what I'm going
to design here now.
And first describe
what the goal is.
And then after that in other
videos we will gradually realize this
example as
UML state diagrams.
I didn't make up the example,
that also comes from Harel's article.
However, he discussed it in
more detail and with more properties.
This is a
simplified variant of the
example Harel used
to motivate his statecharts.
However, this also means that if you like,
you can read about it in the article.
It is supposed to
be about a wristwatch.
A very
simple wristwatch.
It has a display,
an alarm, and two buttons.
What should be
the intuition here?
This below is not
yet a state diagram.
I'm just giving
in a stylized
way how the wristwatch can
present itself, in certain situations.
And will have
arrows in between.
But it won't be
a UML state diagram yet.
Very
important!
So there
is this watch.
It has two buttons, a
and b, left and right.
And it
has two modes.
It can be in
a so-called time display mode.
Then we have just here
in the display the current time.
The hour and minute
hand, but digitally displayed.
Or it can be
in an alarm setting.
You can
set an alarm.
To do that, you first
have to switch to a display
mode, where you can see if
the alarm is on or off.
And then you can turn it on
and off with one of the buttons.
So switch between the
two on and off situations.
For switching, this
button a is meant.
So if we're in
the time display, we
can press the button a and
get into the alarm setting display.
That is what is
supposed to be shown here.
And of course we
can go back from that.
So if we are
in the alarm setting display
and we press a again, we
come back to the time setting.
And we want to
see the current time again.
The alarm can
be on or off.
That's already
shown here.
Of course, we only see
this when we are in the
alarm setting display and
not in the time display.
And then when we're
in this alarm setting display,
we can use the b button to switch
whether the alarm should be on or off.
We are in the alarm display
and the alarm is currently on.
And we press b, then
we're still in the alarm display.
But the
alarm is off.
And of course
it can be undone.
So we can also turn the alarm
back on if we just turned it off.
What is the
effect of this alarm?
It is to
make the clock beep.
It will beep whenever the
time changes to a full hour.
Of course, we don't see
the beeping sound here now.
This is just an information,
it will be simply shown in
the state diagram
in a suitable place:
Beep here
in this transition.
Is it complete
in the meantime?
No
it isn't.
Because in fact it's not meant to say
that when we're in the time display and
we switch to the alarm display,
that then the alarm is always on.
That would
be nonsense.
Let's imagine that we switch to the
alarm setting, then we turn the alarm off.
Then we also want to be
able to switch back to the time.
And not just after
we turn the alarm on.
So there would still have
to be a transition here.
Then here, even if we're in the alarm display
and alarm is off, we want to be able to
switch back to
the time display.
That means the
other way around:
If we wait a few minutes and then press
a again, we don't want to end up here.
After all, we intentionally
turned off the alarm.
We don't want to suddenly find out that
the alarm is on again just because we switched
to the time display and then wanted
to check whether it was on or off.
That's not how
it's supposed to be.
Instead, from the time
display, by pressing a,
we can end up
either here or here.
And that depends on
whether we turned the alarm
on or off the last time
we were in the alarm setting.
And then switched
to the time display.
That may
look non-deterministic here.
That here you don't know what's
going to happen when you press a.
But of course,
implicitly, one already knows.
Because the clock has a hidden state,
whether the alarm is on or off.
So the alarm has
several levels of states.
One, what is
the current time?
Is the alarm
currently on or off?
And am I currently showing the
time or the alarm state/alarm setting?
If you think about it now, if
you wanted to model some flat state diagram,
you would need quite
a lot of states.
One would have to remember, is one
in the alarm or in the time display?
Is the alarm
on or off?
What is
the current time?
Which consists of a number of
hours between 0 and 23, and
a number of minutes
between 0 and 60.
So somehow you would get 2
× 2 × 24 × 60 states.
That is
several thousand.
We do
not want that.
So we look for
a more compact representation.
And this will be realized in analogy to
the example of Harel via a UML state diagram.
In the
following videos.